Shubham Tiwari

PhD student, University of Washington

Research Interests

Broadly interested in the intersection of Systems and AI, currently working on improving the efficiency of serving models in <u>Compound AI Systems</u>. Previously, I have worked on a broad spectrum of problems, for example: memory management optimizations in hypervisors (<u>Mitosis</u>), network measurement, and congestion control (<u>LEOScope</u>, <u>iBox</u>).

Education

University of Washington, *Seattle* Sept 2023 - Present

Ph.D. in Computer Science (ongoing) Advisors: Simon Peter, Ratul Mahajan

Birla Institute of Technology and Science (BITS), Pilani Aug 2016 - July 2021

B.E. Computer Science and M.Sc. Mathematics, CGPA: 8.52

Thesis: Data-Driven Network Simulation with iBox

Experience

Microsoft Research, Redmond June 2024 - Sept 2024

Research Intern with Ishai Menache

Project: Improvements to Azure Compute's VM allocation service.

Microsoft Research, Bangalore Aug 2021 - Aug 2023

Research Fellow with Debopam Bhattacherjee, Venkat Padmanabhan

<u>Projects</u>: LEO Satellite Networks (<u>LEOScope</u>), Data-Driven Network Simulation (<u>iBox</u>)

Microsoft Research, Bangalore Jan 2021 - July 2021

Research Intern with Venkat Padmanabhan, Nagarajan Natarajan

Project: iBox

VMware, Bangalore Aug 2020 - Dec 2020

Intern, xLabs with Jayneel Gandhi

Project: Page-table Replication (Mitosis)

Samsung Research, Bangalore May 2020 - July 2020

Research Intern with Shital Bhatia
Project: Cellular Network Planning

Software-Defined Networking Lab, BITS Pilani Jan 2019 - Dec 2019

Research Assistant with K. Hari Babu

Project: Passive Estimation of Link Latency (qMon)

Publications

C=Conference, J=Journal, P=Preprint

C.1 Boosting Application Performance using Heterogeneous Virtual Channels: Challenges and Opportunities

Talal Touseef, William Sentosa, Milind Kumar Vaddiraju, Debopam Bhattacherjee, Balakrishnan Chandrasekaran, Brighten Godfrey, <u>Shubham Tiwari</u>

 22^{nd} ACM Workshop on Hot Topics in Networks

HotNets'23

P.1 T3P: Demystifying Low-Earth Orbit Satellite Broadband [link]

Shubham Tiwari, Saksham Bhushan, Aryan Taneja, Mohamed Kassem, Cheng Luo, Cong Zhou, Zhiyuan He, Aravindh Raman, Nishanth Sastry, Lili Qiu, Debopam Bhattacherjee

Working paper

arXiv'23

C.2 Simulating Network Paths with Recurrent Buffering Units [link]

Divyam Anshumaan, Sriram Balasubramanian, <u>Shubham Tiwari</u>, Nagarajan Natarajan, Sundararajan Sellamanickam, and Venkata N. Padmanabhan

 37^{th} AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence

AAAI'23

C.3 Data-Driven Network Path Simulation with iBox [link]

Sachin Ashok, <u>Shubham Tiwari</u>, Nagarajan Natarajan, Venkata N. Padmanabhan, and Sundararajan Sellamanickam ACM SIGMETRICS / IFIP PERFORMANCE 2022 SIGMETRICS'22

J.1 qMon: A method to monitor queueing delay in OpenFlow networks [link]

Sandhya Rathee, <u>Shubham Tiwari</u>, K Haribabu, and Ashutosh Bhatia *Journal of Communications and Networks*

JCN'22

Projects

Retrify: Memory-Management Strategies for Efficient Serving of Models in Compound AI Systems April 2024 -

Advisors: Simon Peter, Ratul Mahajan

- > Evaluated various memory-management techniques to improve the performance of long-context requests in Compound AI Systems.
- > Developed a prototype of a serving-system interacting with an external environment to simulate performance of work-loads under various traffic conditions (bursty, variable API call durations).

Optimizations to Azure Compute's VM Allocation Service

June 2024 - Sept 2024

Advisors: Ishai Menache

- > Evaluated the impact of enabling fine-grained VM placement strategies at scale.
- > Proposed changes to resource allocation service with the potential of saving (> \$1M) in operational costs.

LEOScope: Enabling Experimentation Across Low-Earth Orbit (LEO) Satellite Networks

July 2022 - Present

Advisors: Debopam Bhattacherjee, Venkat Padmanabhan [code]

- > Lead an effort with **Azure Space**, **MSRA**, and academic collaborators to build a platform of a global scale for experimentation across Low-Earth Orbit Satellite networks.
- > Drove the effort through engineering challenges such as platform architecture, implementation of experiment scheduler, executor, and the central orchestrator.
- > Initiated large-scale measurements based on ping and iperf to characterize satellite network paths.

iBox: Internet in a Box Jan 2021 - June 2022

Advisors: Venkat Padmanabhan, Nagarajan Natarajan [website]

- > Built a data-driven network simulator that uses data to recreate end-to-end behavior of a network path.
- > Leveraged a combination of internet measurement data and ML models to capture the impact of complex network phenomena such as cross-traffic and packet reordering.
- > Integrated iBox with ns-2, ns-3, netem and Microsoft Teams's in-house network simulator.
- > Resulting papers published at SIGMETRICS'22 and AAAI'23.

qMon: Passive Delay Monitoring in SDNs

Jan 2019 - Dec 2019

Advisor: K. Hari Babu [paper] [code]

- > Devised **qMon**, a scalable latency monitoring technique with zero data plane footprint.
- > Developed an Open vSwitch based prototype to fetch queue length information using OpenFlow and passively estimate link latency.
- > Evaluated qMon on a physical testbed under various traffic scenarios.
- > Resulting paper published at JCN 2022.

Mitosis: Enabling Page-Table Replication in ESXi

Aug 2020 - Dec 2020

Advisor: Jayneel Gandhi

- > Implemented page-table replication (Mitosis) in VMware's core virtualization product ESX.
- > Developed prototypes to disambiguate the design and code needed to support page table replication in the ESX kernel.
- > Conducted workload profiling to estimate the performance benefits of page-table replication; realized gains of upto 17% in workload execution time.

Miscellaneous

- > Awarded a grant of 50,000 INR by AUGSD, BITS Pilani for developing a miniature autonomous driving vehicle.
- > Demonstrated iBox at TAB MSR India's annual technical event.
- > Presented iBox at SIGMETRICS'22. [video]